Smith College.
Smith College Archives
Reif, Nancy Hutchins and Martha Clough Engeman, 1983: In this oral history taken during their 30th reunion weekend, Martha Clough Engeman and Nancy Hutchens Reif, discuss how their meeting as freshmen lead to a lifetime relationship as best friends. They recall traveling to Paris together, including visiting the Smith office and reflect on the importance of Smith traditions, including Friday tea and Thursday night dinners. They remember political controversy on campus, such as an outcry against Jeane Kirkpatrick delivering the commencement address, as well as being on campus during the assassinations of Anwar Sadat and the murder of John Lennon. RESTRICTED TO THE SMITH COMMUNITY/NO ONLINE ACCESS
Roderick, Emma and Justine Sheffler, 2008: In this oral history, Emma Roderick and Justine Sheffler discuss changes in identity politics at Smith since their graduation. They recall social justice movements on campus and the learning that went on outside the classroom, through that activism. They share memories from their time at Smith, including of a favorite J-term origami class. NO ONLINE ACCESS
Rosenthal, Betsy Robins, 1963: In this oral history Betsy Robins Rosenthal recalls her first days at Smith, the divisions she encountered among students along lines of race, religion and class, and the way she's observed diversity increasing on campus over the years. Asked about a "typical Smithie," she reflects on how different Smith students are from one another, but that they are also universally serious students who continually impress her.
Rossen, Susan Friebert, 1963: In this oral history, Susan Friebert Rossen credits her Smith education, particularly her art history professors and her junior year in Paris, with giving her the foundation for a successful professional career. She talks about the experience of helping to prepare her class reunion book and all she learned while researching in the College Archives during that process.
Ross-Reid, Alexandra, 2008: In this oral history, Alexandra Ross-Reid talks about the unique nature and the importance of Smith's house communities. She discusses her perspective as a woman of color and how navigating racial differences and looking at issues from a variety of perspectives during her Smith years prepared her for the world after graduation.
Sclafani, Maria Christina, 2008: In this oral history, Maria Sclafani discusses the central role her house played in her Smith experience. She speaks of professors who played an important role in her Smith education, and recalls a charged political environment that was the backdrop to her college years. She also reflects on how being at Smith gave her an understanding of gender bias and the way that operates in the world, which has informed her post-graduate life. NO ONLINE ACCESS
Sheffler, Justine and Emma Roderick, 2008: In this oral history, Emma Roderick and Justine Sheffler discuss changes in identity politics at Smith since their graduation. They recall social justice movements on campus and the learning that went on outside the classroom, through that activism. They share memories from their time at Smith, including of a favorite J-term origami class. NO ONLINE ACCESS
Simpson-Sawyer, Miranda, 2008: In this oral history, Miranda Simpson-Sawyer recalls the culture shock she experienced on arriving at Smith as a first-year, her favorite Smith traditions, like Convocation, and some of the professors who served as important mentors, and how that influenced her choice of a major.
Smith, Mary Oakes, 1963: In this oral history, Mary Oakes Smith speaks of the ways in which her Smith experience shaped her future activism and her career in international development. She talks about the importance of Smith's Engineering School, and the emphasis on a global education and community service, and recalls professors and classes that presented her with unique opportunities. NO ONLINE ACCESS
Stone, Lysbeth (Libby), 1953: In this oral history, Lysbeth (Libby) Stone, who has only missed one reunion since graduating Smith in 1953, tells stories from her Smith years, recalling that Sylvia Plath was in her Chaucer class and how evident it was that she was a unique talent.
Thorpe, Anne Kingsley, 1943: In this oral history Anne Kingsley Thorpe looks back on her experience of being on campus during World War II, including rushing from classes to listen to reports of critical battles. She remembers Smith traditions which inspired her during her years on campus and the professors who shaped her college career.
Tolles, Martha Gregory, 1943: In this oral history Martha Gregory Tolles recalls her experience being at Smith at the beginning of World War II. She recounts being called into her house mother's sitting room and listening to the news of the attack on Pearl Harbor, as well as work she did for the WAVES. She also tells of meeting her future husband on Mountain Day and recalls working on the college newspaper when Betty Friedan was editor.
Walraven, Berneta, 1983: In this oral history, Berneta Walraven speaks about her the graduation commitment she made to attend Smith reunions and discusses the central role the crew team played in her Smith career. She speaks about her personal identity and political journey, and how that influenced her career as an activist. She discusses the central role the crew team played in her Smith career.
White, Barbara Ehrlich, 1958: In this oral history, Barbara Ehrlich White discusses her view of reunions as markers in our life journey. She looks back on her Smith experience and reflects on the importance of her junior year in Paris in preparing her for her career as an art history professor and author. She credits her Smith training in art history as foundational for her later success. RESTRICTED TO THE SMITH COMMUNITY/NO ONLINE ACCESS
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives except as follows:
2010: No restrictions on use of transcripts or DVDs. Online access permitted with the exception of the following narrators: Katherine Evans, Nina Moe, Sindhumathi Revuluri, Jessica Rowe, Brittain Skinner, and Ana Tolentino. 2011: No restrictions on use of transcripts or DVDs. Online access permitted with the exception of the following narrators: Adele Baydin, Mary Bickerton, Carole DeSanti, Yvonne Johns, Phyllis (Patti) Klein, Marilyn Carson Nelson, Joyce Spencer, Eleanor Woods. 2012: No restrictions on use of transcripts or DVDs with the exception of Patricia Cunningham, Sandra Gleason, and the Group interview 1982, who restricted their interviews to the members of the Smith community. Online access permitted with the exception of the following narrators: Group interview 1957, Paula Duffy, Natalie Field, Marcy Friedman, Marlene Futterman, Jerri Pantages Long, and Brenda Lewis. 2013: No restrictions on use of transcripts or MP4s with the exception of the following interviews, which are open only to the Smith College Community: Jennifer Barone, Alexandra Dellerson, Martha Clough Engeman, Sharon Leyhow, and Catherine Pyun. Online access permitted with the exception of the following interviews: Jennifer Barone, Jennifer Harmon, Alix Kolar, Susan Korgen, Lori Lober, Eileen M. Ouellette, Catherine Pyun, Nancy Hutchens Reif, Emma Roderick, Marjorie Scheffer, Maria Sclafani, Mary Oakes Smith, Martha Gregory Tolles, and Barbara Ehrlich White. Access to Cynthia Kohlbry is by permission of the narrator only.
The Smith College Alumnae Oral History Project collection is comprised of oral histories conducted with alumnae during Reunion weekends in 2010, 2011, 2012 and 2013.
- Evans - Werner 2010 (Box 1)
- Preservation copies and original tapes 2010, RESTRICTED (Box 2)
- Ames - Heller 2011 (Box 3)
- Imbrie - Woods 2011 (Box 4)
- Preservation copies and original tapes 2011, RESTRICTED (Box 5)
- Bershadsky - Kanner 2012 (Box 6)
- Lewis - Sargentini 2012 (Box 7)
- Preservation copies, original tapes, master DVDs 2012, RESTRICTED (Box 8)
- Barone-Lober 2013 (Box 9)
- Maranuk-White 2013 (Box 10)
- Records and release forms 2010-2013, RESTRICTED (Box 11)